okay so so we thought of doing a short
one also showed series on the novella
tellus teachings specifically on his
notes and amo book and venerable Hudson
is behind the camera so he's going to
ask them some questions that are usually
what people ask us about Nevada starting
from preface and then going through
different notes notes of that book so
also if the viewers have any questions
about the Nevada teachings you know
regarding this particular series they
can ask in the comment section and then
we can probably include it in some
future videos so yeah we're gonna start
with preface and then move onwards with
other notes especially the ones that
usually usually people have problems [Music]
[Music]
so I'll start us off with just reading a
section from the first paragraph of the
breakfast he writes there is therefore
nothing in these pages to interest a
professional scholar for whom the
question of personal existence does not
arise for the scholars both concern is
to eliminate or ignore the individual
point of view in an effort to establish
an objective truth it would be
impersonal synthesis of public facts the
scholar is essentially horizontal view
of things
seeking connections in space and time
and his historical approach to the texts
disqualify him many possibility of
understanding ademma that the buddha
himself has called a colleague ax or
timeless only in a vertical view
straight down into the abyss of his
personal existence is a man capable of
apprehending the perilous and security
of his situation
and only a man who does that pretend
this is prepared to listen to the
Buddha's teaching so it it can be a bit
confusing about the idea of having two
different kinds of thinking like what
exactly it is that this thing has a
horizontal kind of thinking as he's
saying versus a vertical kind of
thinking could you elaborate more on
that well in brief the main difference
is the vertical thinking is the thinking
done through through your existence so
you do that thinking arises on the basis
literally on the basis of anxiety
existential dread recognition of your
human situation that's what the Buddha
would often refer in the sutras as a as
a young man would get disillusioned with
life and then he would he would ponder
on human situation he would recognize
this human life is subject to suffering
you are prey to suffering I mean
suffering is this invisible hunter it
can pounce on you at any time and you
can't do anything about it so the main
that'sthat's that's the prerequisite
that a teacher is a prerequisite towards
the return of existential understanding
and then to the right practice of Dhamma
so that's when you know was talking
about when when you're not not trying to
overcome any particular issue that you
might have in your life but really
understanding the nature of a human deal
and and not being satisfied with it so
that's that's that's why you cannot
approach practice correctly as a scholar
or somebody which is merely collecting
information about about about the Dhamma
but you really you really need to make
it not optional for yourself in order to
be able to do it rightly so that's
that's what he meant because often of
the people who approach the suitors
approach the study mostly for the
scholarly value as in collecting the
data collecting information drawing the
pair and space sort of rationalizing it but
and space sort of rationalizing it but
not really approaching it on the basis
of that personal necessity of practice
in which case it's not optional anymore
and you really need to understand what
the Buddha was teaching in order to be
free from the intentional error so what
is it about this vertical view that also
makes it a timeless view as opposed to
the horizontal one that's looking at
connections in space-time well it's as
the Buddha said that the suffering has a
presently reason cause craving which
means that the freedom from suffering
freedom from possibility to suffer which
is a suffering in itself is to be found
in the present moment but not in that
kind of a contemporary mystified notion
of just being the present but in
understanding that pertains to the
present moment as in understanding the
cause of that suffering that's here
presently simultaneously arisen with
that suffering so that is that's what
Nina Vienna Vera Tara described as a
vertical vertical view into into your
own being as opposed to that horizontal
view of you assuming or rationalizing
before and after and in between and left
or right you know seeing prisoner isn't
suffering simultaneously through that
you see presently reason craving and you
know that with the absence of that
craving suffering cannot stand even for
a second longer and that's why it to be
known individually as in vertically
personally by the wise Dhamma that
states timeless in that sense it does
not involve a passage of time that
direct means that doesn't involve it
people in the modern day like
neuroscientists and psychologists and
stuff they also try and study suffering
study maybe apply their fields to the
Buddhist teaching are they using that
vertical view are they divorced from
that in some way
well then they're divorced from that
long time ago when they when they sort
of gave the the the young question
validity to the scientific method
because science in itself negates the
observer while certainly that's the
that's the starting premise later on
they might try to factor in the observer
but only through that scientifically
assumed external public world of matter
and then you try to really observe it
but you failed to see that the observer
was the one who was first he was the one
who decided to look for these particular
things and develop science out of it
which means you can't use them that
science to explain the tools of your
perception of a feeling of your point of
view that as an observer you are
inseparable from yet that whole that
whole domain that hosts fear disappears
in science and when it's included its
included as a second-best so then
whenever a modern science talks about
Buddhism as as if like they're they're
proving the Buddhist teaching to be
right they have completely misunderstood
it to begin with
because if the scientists were truly
understanding that the Buddha was right
they would have been at least they would
become at least the sort of honor
through their science probably other
hunts as well but they're not they are
not free from sensuality greed aversion
delusion wrong view which means when
they say this is what the Buddha meant
they don't know what the Buddha meant
because only well nobody short in a sort
of honor knows what the Buddha meant
correctly and that's one of the things
that was always insisted upon which is a
good thing to be to insist on because he
might be unpleasant to admit to yourself
especially if you invested years of
practice but ultimately it can actually
spur you further because you don't make
a compromise thinking to know that which
you don't and and you keep striving
until you reach that clarity of
knowledge which is necessary
going for any I mean any karate practice
Oh Donna okay I'll start reading now so
going to the next part to page 12 of the
Roman numeral 12 of the preface it
starts existential philosophies then
insist upon asking questions about self
and the world taking care at the same
time to insist that they're unanswerable
beyond this point of frustration these
philosophies cannot go the Buddha too
insists that questions about the self
and the world are unanswerable either by
refusing to answer them or by indicating
that no statement about the self in the
world can be justified but and here is
the vital difference the Buddha can and
does go beyond this point not to be sure
by answering the unanswerable look like
showing the way leading to the final
cessation of all questions about the
self and the world so one one issue that
we can sometimes have when we're trying
to start reading none of your is it all
sounds so very like kind of lofty and
philosophical you know talking about
existential ambiguity for some for some
people it may be hard to see the
connection between this vague
existential problem and just you know
the suffering I have when things don't
go my way for example could you could
you talk about how suffering all does
kind of come to be rooted fundamentally
in this this problem the problem of
existence yeah but the reason why
Univera approach it through the
existential philosophy is because he
himself
we write quite a lot of it because he
wasn't existential philosophy like
Sartre Heidegger well even even Kierkegaard is
Heidegger well even even Kierkegaard is
considered to be part of that it's not
really a philosophy in a sense of a
system of a thought that you develop and
again rationalize or idealize but it's
it's it really in its root obviously
some of those philosophers have went
further afterwards but initially the
whole point of residential philosophy
was to to found to be like a descriptive
method of the phenomenological insight
and saying phenomenological inside
nothing other than saying a mindful
discernment and and that's why that
philosophy was useful for a European
thought because most of the other
philosophies were tending to forget the
existence of the subject as a priority
as they would say existence precedes the
essence and then the whole descriptive
method developed around just seeing
what's present they're not developing
conclusions based upon it so that's when
you know where to pick that up as a
starting point for a petitioner because
that's the that's the most you can get
as a petitioner to clarify the issue of
your situation is highly get described
the in the in the heart of every human
situation is a concern it's
fundamentally rooted upon concerned
that's the that's the most primordial
aspect of human being concerned and and
that's nothing other than dukkha in
itself you're not like you're not
specifically concerned about this so
that just the general vague ambiguous
uneasiness lack of easiness lack of ease
and that's that's what dukkha means
means the absence of these so that's
that's why that he would he would use
extension philosophy to relate to the
reader because that was his background
obviously and also it because it would
require the person who velocity to have
some sort of well at least a degree of
that self awareness of their own
existence which means they won't be
coming from some like a mystical point of view
from some like a mystical point of view
some-some devotional inspiration and in
wanting to have you know the-the-the
ecstasy's of meditation like how they
used to translate the jhanas and so on
so many people still have those residues
of those notions as it is some sort of
some transcendental projection through
to the Buddhist practice in some new
astral realm of arahant ship and similar
but it isn't it's just freeing you from
yourself literally freeing you from
greed aversion delusion freeing you from
unwholesome that's what Nibbana is so in
that sense by opting to to not sort of
boat down the instruction he kind of
saved out many people who would have
just casually arrived at it and
misunderstood it there's no doubt about
it so so that was his approach but
obviously you know that was his approach
it can be different approaches but what
cannot be different is the necessity of
that existential concern as the Buddha
said a young man recognized that he's
prey to suffering that's exactly a
description of the entire existence of
philosophy contained just in that one
line in the sutras imagine how would you
feel if you go about every day of your
life feeling you're prey to a hunter but
you don't know where it is who it is
when it's gonna pounce you will feel
very uneasy and that is the definition
of a human situation so that's why
people use sensuality distraction even
anger all the worldly projects to
distract themselves from the basic
insecurities of the situation so that
that's how it relates to that practice
so it sounds like it's what's more
primordial than is not so much always
when things do not go ones way but the
fact that maybe they could that these
these philosophers were pointing at and
jnana Veera it's pointing out they could
what sorry like that it could go wrong
not necessarily yes yeah you don't need
to wait for it to go wrong because
sometimes by that time might be too late
you want to recognize that it could go
wrong they might go wrong and then of
course as the Buddha went step further
and says well eventually
we'll go wrong sickness aging and death
but those are the ultimate examples of
the human situation that can go wrong at
any time
so that's that's why that dukkha is not
like intense acute suffering like you're
being tortured tormented by something
it's the recognition of the possibility
of being affected by suffering and you
wouldn't be able to do anything about it
and that in itself it's it's it's it's a
cause for concern and concern in itself
it's an unpleasant feeling that's due
Kaiser here is the most general
suffering so you've mentioned that jnana
zerah borrowed heavily from an
existential phenomenological approach
his understanding of the Buddhist
teaching do you think it's necessary
important or necessary for a person who
is trying to understand the Dhamma
themselves to become familiar like start
reading softer and Heidegger and things
like that if they haven't been reading
it no no even probably resulting in
wasting waste more waste more time if
you're already familiar yeah it can be
helpful but as I said even in the Veda
was referring to that to those
descriptions to those to that
terminology of existential phenomenology
because well because people who ordered
and the suited could relate with greater
clarity as it gives them a better
starting point so it was just a ficient
way but it's not you know it is as I
said either either you approach it in
that manner or some other manner one
thing that person must have is that
existential concern recognition of its
own existence or human situation so if a
person is if a person is is aware of
that and approaching Dhamma for that
purpose then they don't need to go to
the extension philosophy they just need
to well become mindful of of the of the
feeling the phenomenon of feeling and
mindful of the possibility of things
that they might feel while they're alive
as in become mindful of the possibility
of
one thing that person reading through
the notes can start asking is you know
all these descriptions of various terms
we find in the sutras are great they
really make sense they're really
clarifying but how do I start practicing
meditating these new things like that
the the suit is so general because it's
been a long time ago and the way of that
oral transmission means now they're very
condensed in meaning and very general
instruction which means people can come
from literally the material for the
angles and read the same sister
differently and you can't help that
because the Buddha is not alive anymore
is nobody there was sort of comes from
their time to point you in the right
direction as too hard to read that's why
it is necessary to start with that
existential attitude in itself awareness
because of that you won't be able to go
to wrong in your miss reading of the
suitors which inevitably everybody
starts by miss reading them and then you
will realize yeah you can interpret like
this you can interpret it like this and
you can emulate this but which one of
those ways that you can interpret it
really pertains to that existential
suffering that becomes your criteria for
practice so that's why it's important to
develop that which is quite unpleasant
often results in anxiety and sense of
dread because otherwise a person would
be sort of overly committing to a view
and then they would be reading the
suitors from that point of view and then
defending it and so on and not really
applying it to that existential basis
and if there is their turn to ask is
there like a specific method or
technique by which one does apply it to
that place
most certainly not no if it were the
Buddha would have would have spoke about
it and the closest to method or
technique is what the suitors tell us
developed be restrained by the by the
precepts see the danger in the slightest
fault be moderate in eating spend your days
be moderate in eating spend your days
being mindful and wakeful as in don't
give in to distraction don't give in to
careless thoughts there will in itself
will result in calmness tranquility they
can then result in seeing things clearly
and knowing exactly what you need to
abandon as in the unwholesome thoughts
thoughts the routine greed aversion
delusion their routine distraction and
and desiring craving but yeah there is a
tendency obviously that what I mean a
person if a person does not have that
person that individual personal vertical
criteria of existential angst and
suffering and possibility to suffer it
will be easy then to just give in to the
promise method or a mechanical technique
they can then result what you hope to
result in liberation but really the only
way you can liberate yourself is to come
to grips with your own existence bhava
and and see that you're responsible for
upholding it and then undo it that's
often talking about undoing things so
the closest to method they can result in
understanding which you can come is to
say you have to keep trying to
understand that's it I can tell you do
this to this to this and then that will
automatically result in understanding
because understanding is when you
understood based on the given doubts and
information so inform yourself through
Univera through the suitors and using
the personal criteria of being liable to
suffering because if you understood
things correctly that liability to
suffering should be diminishing and you
will see directly that's why sotapanna
somebody who has reached that first
stage knows exactly what suffering is
what origin of suffering is what
cessation is and what to do to develop
that cessation he's not guessing anymore
he has a direct knowledge into that
so to reiterate them for one who's
trying to develop this proper attitude
and is trying to undertake a study of
the suitors and notes on Dhamma what it
what is then is the proper place of
these of these notes in that pursuit
well the notes are sort of well first of
all they need to live restrained by the
precepts depending on how far they want
to go in their understanding by the
fiber but ideally eight precepts which
means whether you are reading the notes
or reading the suitors if you don't have
the basic virtue being developed
maintained through a practice of
mindfulness and Samadhi that comes out
of it no amount of understanding will
take place it will all be in the
abstract Scholastic theory so the place
of notes is for somebody who does leave
restraint and once wants the work laid
out for them as in what needs to be
understood some people can can handle more of it
some people can can handle more of it
some people less but the point is you
must you do need to understand at least
a degree of the Buddhist teaching so the
notes could help you develop the right
attitude towards the suitors how to read
them whether you will read them just as
an Indian folklore a social commentary
of the times a loose compilation of the
Buddha's utterances all your gonna read
them as districtís most condensed and
most universal as in general
phenomenological description of your
experience because if you start reading
them like that with that attitude you
realize yeah all it takes is to
understand fully one suta and you can be
another hand on account of it if you are
proud if you if you if you approach it
as a fault lord then you can have it all
makes no difference
but if you approach them actually is a
direct description of something that
universally present in every human
experience means then that you need to
see it in order to understand that suta
so that was one of the example is really
kind of I didn't I didn't realize that
because when I was a layman I was
reading the sutras and I found them
useful but I didn't quite understand
well their extent of their importance
until I came across in a winner whoo but
by that time was original to Sartre
Heidegger and other philosophy being in
time being and nothingness so I could
read philosophy and I had no trouble
following it and I was quite familiar
with it so there was one bit when you
never mentioned he gives this this
entire quote from Sartre or Heidegger
maybe the entire page about a human
situation and and so on about the the
senses and sense perception and I
remember I read that quote many times so
he was it was he felt like oh yeah this
is very useful and then he says Paul for
example as the Buddha would say so he
compares what this like pages of this
philosophy said compares and he was just
like one line from the suitors then I
read many times but he never occurred to
me to read it in such a heavily
condensed manner to give it that kind of
importance but then I realize well
actually I should be giving it that kind
of importance because that's how people
at the end of a discus discourse of the
Buddha would have become utter hands or
at least sought upon us and then we read
it today we wonder why's not nothing
happening to me it's because you're not
reading it rightly if you approach every
single line to be condensed with meaning
not in that Scholastic sort of
investigation of the information and
connections with other passages and so
on but genuinely just what it actually
what is describing it phenomenological
what is being described by it
penological hasn't presently right here
right now and if you approach it like
that then you realize yeah one suitor
fully understood can certainly result in
the right view but for that as I just
give the example like when the Buddha I
mean many of us would have just read
over that that deadline when the Buddha
says a young man feels his prey to
suffering subject to suffering so he
goes forth into homeless life oh yeah
yeah of course yeah
but if you stop and think about it just
just that just as two words pray three
words prayed to suffering contains the
entire existence philosophy volumes and
volumes of work centuries phenological
it's all in that attitude that's all the
classic sense philosophy concern of
experiencing concern in regard to the
basic nature of your resistance yet the
Buddha just included in the first line
of every other suitor but then you
realize hallo
so if I read the rest of the suta I have
to have that attitude then because he
would go further that man who feel he's
afraid of suffering goes into homeless
life finds the teaching applies himself
and then becomes a neuron but that's
what I mean so you can you can say no it
was just a social commentary and you
can't debate that because there is no
proof in between what a living person
can say no you arrived you're wrong
but then you ask yourself well why do
you practice is it because some sort of
cultural enrichment or gathering data or
scholastic development or is it for
freedom from suffering then you
recognize the world scholastic
understanding social understanding no
matter how vast the net of your
connection develops does not free from
suffering but phenomenological
understanding the present there isn't
cause of the present there isn't
suffering does for you from and then you
you can decide yourself how you want to
read the sutras
one set of terms that comes up fairly
often is a positive and negative
there's footnote letter n which
describes a brief quote from Soren
Kierkegaard regarding the negative
thinking it says precisely because the negative
it says precisely because the negative
is present in existence
present everywhere for existence is a
constant process of becoming it is
necessary to become aware of its
presence continuously as the only
safeguard against it you know viewer
writes positive or abstract thinking
distracts from existence and is thus
incapable of thinking it continuously so
it's it's not it may not be clear to
many people what exactly what is a what
is a negative for the positive kind of
thinking like those domains may not mean
anything to some people who in simple
terms a negative thinker is a thinker
who is aware of his own situation while
thinking he doesn't abstract the content
of his thoughts from the situation which
is why it's called abstraction so he
remains aware of the background that the
necessary basis for his whatever
engagement might be so that's why the
negative thinker is isn't that it's
negative in relation to the positive
content of his particular thought so he
is kind of like aware of the background
of his act of thinking of speaking or or
doing things by body aware of the
peripheral that's exactly where in the
Sutra that's exactly where the
development of mind comes down to
practice of Samadhi practice of jhana
developing the spare that peripheral and
thus overcoming the particular domains
of sensuality ill-will and so on
so then when one is trying to understand
these notes is it that negative kind of
thinking through which they have to be
understood as those two the positive
thinking that one may be used to well
it's not something you can negative
think it's not something you can jump
into by choice so it needs to be
developed so by trying to understand
what negative thinking is what the
negative thinker is that's how you begin
to develop it so that's what I mean if
you approach it just through like a
positive comparison and scholastic study
and so on and you're not going to
understand the notes but if you approach
it because you want solution to the
exist n shil problem of liability to
suffering then you will start to
understand it because you will be
reading them increasingly more rightly
so so to speak and that's what I mean
the the virtue the restraint the sense
restraint and the the the establishment
of virtue in the precepts needs it's not
negotiable needs to come first and needs
to be maintained beforehand as well
which means then you took it on as your
lifestyle the whole approach to them are
not just as something we might do on the
weekends or occasionally on life or at
the end of the preface preface he talks
about this fundamental structure which
is at the back of the notes and Emma a
lot of people have many many questions
and are very interested in mathematical
appearance do you think that's something
that's important for understanding the
future no absolutely not as he himself said
no absolutely not as he himself said
it's just an instrument of thought the
he himself found very useful but you
can't really think fundamental structure
in phenomenological terms because you
are the structure your experience the
pancham pancham pancham put on a condom
the five aggregates easier experience so
what he deals there with he deals with
with the description of the structure
which would require you to have an
external view to it which you can't so
in order to describe it you must give up
the phonological
to give a phenomenal method you're not
talking about existence anymore that we
referred it is an instrument as a as a
justification for reflexive thinking and
so on as an explanation for it but in
terms of somebody needing to to
understand it or some it's not
necessarily completely because also you
well you cannot factor in in that
structure which is the problem of
science as well they they me the same
problem which is when you assume the
external point of view to your
experience you can't factor in the
feeling the domain of feeling I mean you
can represent it on the paper but that's
not being felt right there and then so
in that sense feeling he's always
present but they remember the past field
in the future field in the present
feeling you feel it presently
hence the Buddha said my teachings for
the one who feels who knows how to feel
so that's why I wouldn't unless unless
you already have a starting point that
allows you to relate to fundamental
structure and can kind of just enrich
the instrument of off of your thinking
that's fine but otherwise you've just
wasted time I think I think he included
it because it's it is quite unique and
for for somebody was in philosophy and
phenomenology yeah it's it's it's a very
interesting and useful thing in that
semi semi scholastic semi
phenomenological sense you